<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Mind for Language - interviews</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/interviews.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>How'd you get here: an interview with Seumas McDonnald</title><link href="/howd-you-get-here-an-interview-with-seumas-mcdonnald.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Fletcher Hardison</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-11-18:/howd-you-get-here-an-interview-with-seumas-mcdonnald.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On 18/19 Nov 2019 (depending on your time zone) Dr. Seumas McDonnald and I chatted about Greek and how he got to his current level in Greek. Seumas is a Greek teacher and researcher who runs The Patrologist.com. He is working on a number of projects to create …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On 18/19 Nov 2019 (depending on your time zone) Dr. Seumas McDonnald and I chatted about Greek and how he got to his current level in Greek. Seumas is a Greek teacher and researcher who runs The Patrologist.com. He is working on a number of projects to create Greek teaching/learning materials that reflect what linguistics has taught us about how humans learn languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing he repeated a few times was that it took him a lot longer than it needed to, because of the methods used and that using proper CI based methods, it shoudn't take near as long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;It starts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many of us, Seumas started in traditional grammar-translation type classes. He began with Mounce's &lt;em&gt;Basics of Biblical Greek&lt;/em&gt; which he worked through on his own before entering a theological degree. In that program, he was required to take four years. The first year was largely what he covered in Mounce's book and then the second year moved on to Wallace's Greek Grammar Beyond the Basics. The last two years would were exegesis classes based on the Greek text. He also began studying Latin on the side during this time. Additional Greek input came from taking some classes at another school on works written in the Attic dialect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Journey to CI&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It started with &lt;em&gt;Lingua Latin Per Se Illustrata&lt;/em&gt;. This book pushed Seumas to realize that there were other ways to learn languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Last few years&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to brigde teh vobab gap&lt;/h1&gt;</content><category term="interviews"></category><category term="greek"></category><category term="interview"></category><category term="ci"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="learning"></category></entry></feed>