<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Mind for Language - memory</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/memory.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2018-07-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>What makes a good mnemonic image?</title><link href="/what-makes-a-good-mnemonic-image.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-07-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Fletcher Hardison</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-07-13:/what-makes-a-good-mnemonic-image.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What if I told you that a simple, still image can be all you need to create a mnemonic with real sticking power?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/daniel-hjalmarsson-597537-unsplash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might think that's nuts. You've probably heard that mental images need to be bright, colorful, crazy, perhaps obscene, and fully of action. While I agree that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What if I told you that a simple, still image can be all you need to create a mnemonic with real sticking power?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/daniel-hjalmarsson-597537-unsplash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might think that's nuts. You've probably heard that mental images need to be bright, colorful, crazy, perhaps obscene, and fully of action. While I agree that this can work for some people, I don't believe that it is necessary &amp;ndash; or even the most effective &amp;ndash; for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a mnemonist for whom complicated, action filled images don't work. If you feel overwhelmed by having to invent action filled stories for each thing you want to memorize, let me propose an alternative for your consideration that I learned about through Swedish author, teacher, and Grand Master of Memory &lt;a href="http://www.grandmasterofmemory.com/"&gt;Mattias Ribbing&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I listened to everything of Ribbing's that I could find and finally decided to learn to read Swedish so I could read his books. This post is primarily based on his book &lt;a href="https://www.adlibris.com/se/bok/vagen-till-mastarminne-forandra-ditt-liv-med-kraftfull-minnestraning-9789172322646"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Way to a Master Memory&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Characteristic of a memory friendly image&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core of many memory techniques is converting information into an image. Ribbing has his own take on how to do this based on the &lt;a href="http://www.sevensigma.info/articles/4memory.html"&gt;Giordano Memory System&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/art-close-up-comic-16516.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He begins with the principle that we can't memorize things in isolation, rather they they need to be connected. So visualizing one image by itself is not helpful. We need to create couplings of images that touch, sit on, or even pierce each other in some way. If you are memorizing texts or foreign language vocabulary, then connecting images makes things easier anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ribbing says "To be able to quickly create good couplings [of images], we need to to visualize &lt;em&gt;memory-friendly images&lt;/em&gt;" (clarification added). He sets forth the following criteria for what qualifies as a memory-friendly image:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means images of physical objects that we can see in front of us in the room, big, in color, three-dimensional and detailed. The images must also have contours that clearly delimit them from the environment (Ribbing 2011, &lt;em&gt;translation mine&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also adds that we should use the first image that comes to mind that fulfills these criteria. Finally, that image should be &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this sounds like a lot, that's ok. It becomes nearly automatic with practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The principles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have rephrased his criteria so that they can be remembered with the phrase "TeDDy'S CaFe." Imagine Winnie the Pooh having a coffee in Starbucks or your café of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;hree dimensional&lt;/em&gt;, not flat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;istinct&lt;/em&gt; and has clear contours (sharp angles are a bonus too)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;etailed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;till&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it's &lt;em&gt;in &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;olor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F&lt;/strong&gt;irst image I think up&lt;/em&gt; that has the above characteristics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image below is the size of an index card and can be printed and kept with you as a reminder of these principles (a PDF is available &lt;a href="/images/TeDDy_CaFe.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/TeDDy_CaFe.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two final points from Ribbing and my own experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try to imagine the image in front of you taking up space.&lt;/strong&gt; This takes some practice but I think it pays off. I often look to where various parts of it would be if it were really in front of me. Ribbing has said in some of his talks that this helps (find out more &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_CFtPOUx7Hk"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6e9PxI66tyI"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). I agree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you visualize an image, take a few seconds to really see it. Notice what details that your mind provides.&lt;/strong&gt; Even if you just imagine a book, your brain is probably thinking of a specific book. So take the time to see what book you are seeing in your mind. Chronicles of Narnia? Lord of the Rings? Oxford English Dictionary?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I wanted to use a knight to remember England (I was memorizing World Cup wins at the time). As I paid attention to the details, I realized that I was imagining a crusader knight with a red cross and white tunic over his armor. These details make the image "sticky" mentally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Encoding techniques&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking up images can be challenging when we first begin. Ribbing describes three kinds of encoding strategies that we can use to convert information to images. I don't consciously think "Oh, I'm using a symbolic encoding right now," but knowing that these three techniques are solid strategies can give direction when you don't know how to encode something. They can also give you assurance that you are doing things the right way when you have doubts. Doubt is something I think we all experience when learning memory techinques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consonance encoding (&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; sounds like &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Symbolic encoding (&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; is closely associated with &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experiential encoding (&lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; relates to &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; in my personal experience)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Consonance encoding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;strong&gt;consonance encoding&lt;/strong&gt; (think rhyming) we use a similar sounding word to encode the information we want to memorize. Ribbing notes that this is especially useful for learning foreign language vocabulary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, to learn the Spanish word &lt;em&gt;casa&lt;/em&gt; 'house', we might use the English word &lt;em&gt;cash&lt;/em&gt; to help remember the pronunciation. So our mental image would be a house made out of cash.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Symbolic encoding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this kind of encoding we use a symbol to encode the new information. For example, a heart is often used as a symbol for "love". A flag could be used in place of the country it represents. The idea is to use something closely associated with thing to be remembered as a replacement/stand in for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Experiential encoding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With experiential encoding we encode information using a personal connection. For example, I memorized the word &lt;em&gt;Benjaminite&lt;/em&gt; by using an baby blue electric guitar because a good friend of mine whose middle name is Benjamin plays a baby blue Fender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use this technique find something from your experience that helps you remember the new information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the technique you choose, the image you create should follow the "TeDDy'S CaFe" principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many memory technique teachers recommend using bright, action-filled stories to convert information into something that can stick in long-term memory. However, that's not the case for all memory teachers. I personally find creating such images difficult and that all the action makes them hard to visualize.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I prefer to use "TeDDy'S CaFe" style images. I find them less stressful to work with and more effective for me. When looking for images, we can encode information using one of three time tested teqniques: rhyming, symbolic association, or by using something from our own experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter where you come down on action filled or still images, the other principles of what makes a memory-friendly (mnemonic) image will help you strengthen your skills as a mnemonist, help you memorize things faster, and remember them for longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy memorizing!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="memory"></category></entry><entry><title>How to Memorize Scripture and Have Fun Doing it</title><link href="/how-to-memorize-scripture-and-have-fun-doing-it.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Fletcher Hardison</name></author><id>tag:None,2018-06-06:/how-to-memorize-scripture-and-have-fun-doing-it.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What if I told you it's possible to memorize Scripture without boring repetition? You might think I'm crazy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/bibleImageGeneric.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible, however. In fact, it becomes a creative, almost gamelike process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that most of us approach memorization without a mnemonic method. What is a mnemonic method you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What if I told you it's possible to memorize Scripture without boring repetition? You might think I'm crazy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/bibleImageGeneric.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible, however. In fact, it becomes a creative, almost gamelike process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that most of us approach memorization without a mnemonic method. What is a mnemonic method you say?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mnemonic is simply a memory friendly device like a acronym or mental story that allows us to encode non-memorable information in a memory friendly way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This course will give you the ability to memorize Scripture in less time and remember it longer. We will do this by learning to select keywords, encode Scripture into memory friendly mental images, link these images, and fix them in memory for long term retention.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to memorize Scripture and make it stick: Overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The method has four steps and we can remember them using the phrase "KEy LoaF" (It's the &lt;em&gt;key&lt;/em&gt; to memorizing our &lt;em&gt;daily-bread&lt;/em&gt;, thus "loaf"). Each step will be explained in the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#pick-keywords"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pick &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt;eywords&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from the verse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#encode-keywords-as-mental-images"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;ncode keywords&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#link-images-to-a-memorable-location"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L&lt;/strong&gt;ink images&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to a memorable location&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="#Fixing-images-for-long-term-retention"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F&lt;/strong&gt;ix images&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in memory for long term retention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before diving into these steps, we're going to begin with some theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;You don't need to memorize every word&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to begin with a principle that you may not agree with, but hear me out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You don't need to memorize every word perfectly.&lt;/strong&gt; Unless your goal is a memory competition, forcing yourself to memorize every little "this" and "that" perfectly will only create fatigue and make you more likely to give up on Scripture memory &amp;ndash; or at least stop enjoying the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your goal is &lt;em&gt;edification&lt;/em&gt;, then the content is more important than having every tiny detail perfect. As an aside, unless you're memorizing in Greek, Hebrew, or Aramaic, you're memorizing a translation anyway. Thus there are little details that translators need to add or skip over in order to translate well because no two languages are 100% alike. So some of those little details aren't in the original anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, if you're like me, you want to be able to recall the verse with a high degree of accuracy. This desire helps us determine how many and what keywords need to be encoded &amp;ndash; more on that in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also two other reasons that we don't need to stress about encoding every word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We don't need to memorize each word perfectly because our knowledge of English grammar helps us fill in the details.&lt;/strong&gt; For example, what word goes in the blank, "He looked ___ her". Your knowledge of English tells you that either "at" or "for" must go in the gap. The context of the verse will probably let you fill in this detail without having to figure out a way to memorize it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You don't need to memorize every word because there are patterns in the text that can help us fill in details.&lt;/strong&gt; For example, what goes in the following blanks?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Blessed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;are&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;poor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;spirit&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;theirs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;kingdom&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;heaven&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;____&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;who&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;mourn&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="nv"&gt;___&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;they&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;shall&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;be&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;comforted&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;____&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;peacemakers&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="nv"&gt;___&lt;/span&gt; ...
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you guessed "Blessed are" and "for", you're right. The patterns in this text mean that we can fill in the gaps. This means that we may only need to fully encode the first line ("Blessed are the poor in spirit ...") and we'll get the rest for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Pick keywords&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/black-and-white-dark-keys-792031.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step in memorizing a verse of Scripture is to &lt;strong&gt;determine what words you need to encode (covert into images) in order to accurately recall the verse.&lt;/strong&gt; We call these words "keywords". Don't worry about what "encoding" means just yet. We'll cover that in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will apply the following principles to help determine what keywords we need to encode:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does my knowledge of English grammar help me fill in this word?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there a pattern in the text so that I can remember this word/phrase without encoding it (every time)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I able to accurately recall the verse without encoding this word?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principle 3 trumps the previous two. If you feel that you can accurately recall a verse without encoding a word, great. If you feel that you can't, then encode it anyway, even though you could probably fill it in from a pattern or from your knowledge of English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's take I Cor 1:26 as an example (below). What words do you need to accurately recall from memory? The answer to this question will be different for each person. I've bolded the ones that I would probably pick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;consider&lt;/strong&gt; your &lt;strong&gt;calling&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;brothers&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;not many&lt;/strong&gt; of you were &lt;strong&gt;wise&lt;/strong&gt; according to &lt;strong&gt;worldly standards&lt;/strong&gt;, not many were &lt;strong&gt;powerful&lt;/strong&gt;, not many were of &lt;strong&gt;noble birth&lt;/strong&gt;. (ESV, &lt;a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+Corinthians+1%3A26-29&amp;amp;version=ESV"&gt;Biblegateway.com&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my keyword list is: consider, calling, brothers, not many, wise, worldly standards, powerful, noble birth. This means that I need to memorize 8 things to memorize this verse accurately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that "keywords" can be phrases like "not many" or "worldly standards."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homework&lt;/strong&gt;: Pick a verse you want to memorize and identify the keywords you will need to accurately recall the verse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Encode keywords as mental images&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/art-close-up-comic-16516.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have our keywords, we need to &lt;strong&gt;encode them as memory friendly images.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the fun and difficult part. It takes some practice and trial and error to learn how to do this, but it is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different memory teachers teach encoding different ways. Some say that images should include action, emotion, and involve as many of the senses as possible. Others say that simpler, clear images are sufficient. I'm generally in the later camp. I find them easier to create and picture in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="/2018/07/13/a-good-mnemonic-image.html"&gt;memory friendly image&lt;/a&gt; is one that has the following characteristics (from &lt;a href="http://www.sevensigma.info/articles/4memory.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), which we can remember with the phrase "TeDDy'S CaFe." Imagine a Winnie the Pooh having a coffee in Starbucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;hree dimensional&lt;/em&gt;, not flat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;istinct&lt;/em&gt; and has clear contours (sharp angles are a bonus too)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;D&lt;/strong&gt;etailed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;till&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it's &lt;em&gt;in &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;olor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F&lt;/strong&gt;irst image I think up&lt;/em&gt; that has the above characteristics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people like to make these images move and interact. &lt;em&gt;I generally prefer still images.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, enough theory! Let's encode some keywords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I think of "consider", an open book is the first thing that pops into my head. A book is 3D, it's distinct and has clear contours and sharp angles. I can imagine the size, red ribbon bookmark, the shape of the paragraphs on the page and the large drop capital letter at the start of the first paragraph. I can picture the page numbers and heading, the color of the paper and the ink. Thus it is detailed and in color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For "calling", I imagine a black rotary dial telephone. You know, with the stainless steel rotary with the white ceramic name plate in the middle and the curly, black cord?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll probably combine these two images and imagine the phone sitting on top of the open book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For "Brothers", you could imagine something reminds you of your own brother. I've read that people are not the best mental images because most people have the same basic shape and aren't very distinct. Instead, you could use something associated with that person. Since I don't have any siblings, I think of brown monk's habit like Friar Tuck wears in the animated Robin Hood movie. It's brown, has a hood, and is a bit dirty.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Repeat this process for each keyword&lt;/em&gt; and combine them into one image if you think it makes sense and will help you remember them. If not, you don't need to combine them. Combining images means that you have less separate images to link in the next step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another tip I've learned is &lt;em&gt;notice what details you're imagining as you imagine an image.&lt;/em&gt; Even if you just think to imagine a book, your brain is probably thinking of a specific book. So take a minute and see what book you are seeing in your mind? Chronicles of Narnia? Lord of the Rings? Oxford English Dictionary? For another example, I wanted to use a knight to remember England (I was memorizing World Cup wins at the time). As I paid attention to the details, I realized that I was imagining a crusader knight with the red cross and white tunic over his armor. These details make the image "sticky" mentally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homework&lt;/strong&gt;: Encode the keywords from your verse using the TeDDy'S CaFe principles. You might also want to write down what images you came up, but you don't have to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Link images to a memorable location&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/boat-chain-dawn-119562.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third step is to &lt;strong&gt;link the images to a memorable location&lt;/strong&gt;. The goal is to provide structure and order to the images so that we have a way to mentally "look" for them. By linking our mental images to a physical location or object, we have a way to locate them when we need them. For example, if I know that John 1 is linked to places in my living room, then I can mentally look there when I want to recall John 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few techniques to link images. I will talk about two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The journey method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also know as the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Method_of_loci"&gt;method of loci&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href="https://artofmemory.com/wiki/How_to_Build_a_Memory_Palace"&gt;memory palace technique&lt;/a&gt;, this method relies on using a physical space that is well known to store the images made during the encoding step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get a sense for the power of this method, stop and try to remember as many details about your bedroom as you can. Imagine yourself walking in the door; then move around the room clockwise. What do you see? Where is your dresser relative to your bed? What about the closet? My guess is that you can remember the furniture, windows, doors, artwork, and other details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As humans, we remember physical spaces very easily and in great detail. By tying the information we want to remember to a physical space, it becomes much easier to remember it. Also, because we will mentally walk through the space in a set order, it becomes easier to recall things in a set order, which is what we want when memorizing Scripture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;To use this method:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick an indoor location that you know well.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example&lt;/em&gt;: your house, job, parents' house, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify a number of places that are distinct within this place. These are called stations.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example&lt;/em&gt;: bed, side table, dresser, bathroom door, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick an order that you will mentally visit these stations with the following characteristics:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don't have to cross your path or double back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The order is obvious so you don't have to think about it. Deciding that you will go clockwise around the room works well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example&lt;/em&gt;: front door mat, kids bookcase, side table, recliner, lamp, chair, bookcase, kitchen door, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optional: draw a rough map and number the stations. &lt;a href="https://www.magneticmemorymethod.com/free-memory-improvement-kit/"&gt;Dr. Anthony Metivier&lt;/a&gt; views this as vital to making the palace "magnetic".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begin imagining the images you created during the encoding step on the stations you picked out. One image per station and the images should touch the station in some way.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example&lt;/em&gt;: I might imagine an open book with a phone sticking out from my bedroom door like a shelf.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can place images on stations however you like as long as it's easy to remember. &lt;em&gt;As a generally rule, take about two seconds to visualize the station, then take two seconds to visualize the images you want to store there, then take two seconds to visualize the image on/in/under the station (see &lt;a href="http://www.sevensigma.info/articles/4memory.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This probably seems complicated, but we can boil down: pick a place you know well, pick a few places in there, pick a route, and put the images on those places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The supporting image method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is basically the same as the journey method, but instead of picking a physical space, we pick an object that has enough distinct parts that we can use to store images. We call this object a "supporting images". For example, we might store images in/on a car, a refrigerator, a bookcase, a desk, or a lawnmower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;To use this method:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick an object that you can visualize clearly that has sufficient distinct parts. (You need to know how many keyword images you have.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide what parts you are going to use as stations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick an order that you will go through these stations. Left to right, top to bottom is a simply way to ensure consistency (from &lt;a href="http://www.sevensigma.info/articles/4memory.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link the images form the encoding phase with the stations of your supporting image as you did in the journey method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Once you are comfortable with the method you can combine the encoding and the linking phases and link a keyword to a station as soon as you encode it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have your images linked to the stations of a journey or supporting image, you can mentally go over that journey or image and decode each image to recall the Scripture stored there. This will be slow at first, but decoding will become faster (almost automatic) as you go over the images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homework&lt;/strong&gt;: decide which method you are going to use and create a journey or supporting image and link the keywords you encoded to that route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Fixing images for long term retention&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/board-broken-builder-209235.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final step of the method is to &lt;strong&gt;fix the images in long term memory&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any memory will fade if it is not recalled frequently enough. This is especially true with something like Scripture. We overcome this by repeatedly going over the mental journey we created in the linking step and decoding the images stored there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to review intensively for the first 4 days. After that, the verse should be pretty well "stuck" in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic &lt;em&gt;review formula&lt;/em&gt; is: &lt;code&gt;next review = last review * 2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, if my last review was after 2 days, then my next review will be after 4 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suggest the follow review schedule:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 hours later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 hours later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The next morning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 days later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 days later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can add more reviews if you like. Just use the review formula above to schedule them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="http://www.sevensigma.info/articles/4memory.html"&gt;Rolph's summary of the Giordano Memory System&lt;/a&gt;, after the intensive review period, information needs to be reviewed every 6 weeks or it will begin to fade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This schedule may seem a bit overwhelming, but we can simplify it by tying reviews to meal times. If you memorize in the morning, then your first review would be at lunchtime, your second after dinner/before bed, then the next morning, 2 days, 4 days, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can add reminders to your calendar so you won't forget the reviews. Another trick is to use a Leitner Box which you can read about &lt;a href="https://www.virtualsalt.com/learn10.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or watch a tutorial &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HN0OUnLxFeU&amp;amp;list=WL&amp;amp;index=55&amp;amp;t=106s"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homework&lt;/strong&gt;: Review the route you created and decode the images at least two times today and then tomorrow morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations, you've just learned a method to memorize Scripture faster and remember it longer (KEy LoaF). Instead of rote repetition, we identify &lt;strong&gt;keywords&lt;/strong&gt;,  &lt;strong&gt;encode&lt;/strong&gt; them as memory friendly images (TeDDy'S CaFe), &lt;strong&gt;link&lt;/strong&gt; them to a memorable location, and &lt;strong&gt;fix&lt;/strong&gt; them in long term memory by recalling them on a specific schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method is not &lt;em&gt;difficult&lt;/em&gt;, but does take some getting used to. For me the hardest part is thinking up images to encode keywords, but this gets easier with practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy memorizing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;P.S.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm more than happy to teach this method in a workshop format to your group (large or small). Sometimes you just need someone to walk you through the process and answer questions. Email me at &lt;a href="mailto:fletcher@amindforlanguage.com?subject=[A%20Mind%20for%20Language]:"&gt;fletcher@amindforlanguage.com&lt;/a&gt; and we can figure out what's right for you and your group.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="memory"></category><category term="theory"></category><category term="method"></category><category term="memory"></category></entry></feed>