<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Mind for Language - syriac</title><link href="https://amindforlanguage.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://amindforlanguage.com/feeds/syriac.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://amindforlanguage.com/</id><updated>2019-06-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Learning Syriac - project index</title><link href="https://amindforlanguage.com/learning-syriac-project-index.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-06-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Fletcher Hardison</name></author><id>tag:amindforlanguage.com,2019-06-12:/learning-syriac-project-index.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Syriac is a Semitic language in the same family as Aramaic. It also has one of the earliest transitions the New Testament and is a Christian literary language as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's related to the Aramaic that Jesus and the Apostles would have grown up speaking...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... and it's not widely known …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Syriac is a Semitic language in the same family as Aramaic. It also has one of the earliest transitions the New Testament and is a Christian literary language as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's related to the Aramaic that Jesus and the Apostles would have grown up speaking...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... and it's not widely known ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... and doesn't have near the resources available as do Greek, Hebrew, or Latin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hope is that this series of posts will help throw some light on how to learn it by describing my experience as I'm doing just that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider this an experiment and a test to see if some of the techniques that I have found effective with Koine Greek work for another ancient language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Principles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the principles that guide how I'm going to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input over grammar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amindforlanguage.com/2019/05/16/anki-cloze-tables.html"&gt;Cloze grammar cards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amindforlanguage.com/2019/06/10/spaced-reading.html"&gt;Spaced, repeated reading&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Input over grammar&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, time spent reading &lt;em&gt;Syriac&lt;/em&gt; will be more effective than time spent reading &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; Syriac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As long as what I'm reading is qualifies as &lt;em&gt;comprehensible input&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. at least 95% understandable).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with classical languages is finding material that qualifies as comprehensible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I'm a beginner, my plan is to start by adding the sentences from my text book to an &lt;a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/"&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt; flashcard deck. I'll make sure that I understand the translation of these sentences before I add them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the Syriac writing system is quite different from what I'm used to and has a lot of silent letters. I'm going to include a rough phonetic transcription on the back of each card along with the translation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another trick I learned is to bold new vocabulary that you want to learn. This will be more useful after I'm more comfortable reading and don't need a full translation on each card. At that point, I'll stop adding full translations and just note the meaning of the bolded words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cloze grammar cards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more details see &lt;a href="http://amindforlanguage.com/2019/05/16/anki-cloze-tables.html"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is to use cloze deletions to become more familiar with the paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These seem to work really well for me to become comfortable with how a paradigm works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is in tension with the &lt;code&gt;input over grammar&lt;/code&gt; principle above, but I find such &lt;em&gt;familarity&lt;/em&gt; to be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, not memorizing to memorize, but familiarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Spaced, repeated reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="http://amindforlanguage.com/2019/06/10/spaced-reading.html"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short the idea is to use &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaced_repetition"&gt;spaced repetition&lt;/a&gt; to schedule rereading material that qualifies as comprehensible input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is accomplished by using a spaced repetition software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me this is Anki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning, the cards will simple be the sentences from my textbooks. Once I'm more comfortable, then the cards will probably be links, book + page numbers, or references to the material that I want to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What's next&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write other posts about learning Syriac, I'll add links to them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="syriac"></category><category term="syriac"></category><category term="studying"></category><category term="techniques"></category><category term="principles"></category><category term="anki"></category></entry></feed>