<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Mind for Language - teaching</title><link href="http://amindforlanguage.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://amindforlanguage.com/feeds/teaching.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://amindforlanguage.com/</id><updated>2018-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>What do you have? - an input task for introducing new vocab in Greek</title><link href="http://amindforlanguage.com/what-do-you-have-an-input-task-for-introducing-new-vocab-in-greek.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Fletcher Hardison</name></author><id>tag:amindforlanguage.com,2018-11-09:/what-do-you-have-an-input-task-for-introducing-new-vocab-in-greek.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the problems facing learners of Ancient is getting used to the cases of nouns. Below is a simple input task that can be used to introduce new vocabulary. Students are given an item and a card with the name of that item. They are then asked to find …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the problems facing learners of Ancient is getting used to the cases of nouns. Below is a simple input task that can be used to introduce new vocabulary. Students are given an item and a card with the name of that item. They are then asked to find out what other students have and if the other students like that item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will allow students to expand their vocabulary as well as encounter that vocabulary in both nominative and accusative case. This should work for nouns, some participles, and adjectives if used in conjunction with a noun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Prep&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find props, pictures, or other realia that represents the words to be learned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a card that has the Greek word for that object. Make sure to include the article and/or genitive singular of the word so that students can correctly identify what gender it belongs to.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It may also be necessary to give the accusative case depending on students facility in conjugating the given declension.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If students are beginners, it may help to give them the sentences they will need to complete this activity (see "Language needed for this activity" below).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Setup&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Divide students into groups if necessary. Ideally one or two vocabulary items per student.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give students a prop and a card with the new vocabulary item.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tell students that they need to learn the name of each object/picture/etc. in their group and whether the person likes it because they will be asked to tell the class this information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Wrap up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After students have found the information, the teacher can pick students from the group to tell the class the objects and if the other student liked the item. This also provides a chance to the teacher to repeat the basic questions "τι έχει ...?" and "ᾶρα αυτῄῳ αρέσει ο/η/τό ___?".  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Language needed for this activity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;τι έχεις?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;έχω (ένα/μίαν/έν) ___.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ᾶρα σοι αρέσει ο/η/τό ___&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;μοι (ου) αρέσει ο/η/τό __&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;έχει ο/η name-of-student ___.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;αυτῳ/αυτῃ αρέσει ο/η/τό ___&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="teaching"></category></entry><entry><title>Limiting vocabulary in highly inflected (and irregular) languages</title><link href="http://amindforlanguage.com/limiting-vocabulary-in-highly-inflected-and-irregular-languages.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Fletcher Hardison</name></author><id>tag:amindforlanguage.com,2018-11-08:/limiting-vocabulary-in-highly-inflected-and-irregular-languages.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ancient/Koine Greek is nothing if not inflected. It is also quite irregular. This is a pain for students because of the many, many forms a given word can take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One principle of modern language teaching is to "limit" or "shelter" vocabulary. In other words, don't use too many new …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ancient/Koine Greek is nothing if not inflected. It is also quite irregular. This is a pain for students because of the many, many forms a given word can take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One principle of modern language teaching is to "limit" or "shelter" vocabulary. In other words, don't use too many new words in the course of a lesson and don't teach too many words in the course. The corollary to this is usually not to limit grammar. Thus while students may only hear a small number of new words, they hear normal (complex) grammar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The problem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://amindforlanguage.com/images/mark-rasmuson.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my Koine Greek class I have tried to limit the number of vocabulary items. I only add a few new words per lesson, but these words are drawn from each gender: masculine, feminine, and neuter. This gives students a chance to acquire the different declensions and the definite article that goes with them. The trouble is that some of these (quite common) words have stem changes and this adds to what my students have to deal with. Even though this kind of suppletion is common in Greek, I think it is overwhelming for my students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The solution &amp;ndash; maybe&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been listening to &lt;a href="http://www.teawithbvp.com/"&gt;Tea with BVP&lt;/a&gt; and their new podcast &lt;a href="https://www.classroomtapas.com/talkinl2"&gt;Talkin' L2 with BVP&lt;/a&gt;. Bill VanPatten (i.e. BVP) notes that paradigms aren't psychologically real. In other words, they don't exist in students' brains. Instead, each form is acquired as a separate word and only after a lot of acquisition has already happened are connections made between forms. BVP also notes that when students want to produce a new form, their brain strips the ending off a word in their mental lexicon and applies it to create the new form (again, no paradigms).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thinking about this brought me to the realization that I need to consider each form a word to be a separate word for the purpose of limiting vocabulary.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What does this mean?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://amindforlanguage.com/images/cynthiadelrio.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think that this means that I should only introduce three to four forms if one word per lesson. I'd never get anywhere with my students. Rather, I should try to introduce words from the same declension so that students don't have to juggle too many new patterns per lesson. This will help expose them to the same kinds of words and hopefully provide the examples and repetition they need to learn the words and make connection between their various forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In upcoming lessons, I will focus introduce words from the same declension (as much as possible). If these words have a stem change, then I may lower the number of new vocabulary items for that lesson and focus on repetitions of the forms with the stem change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hope is that by considering different forms as separate words and by drawing new vocabulary from the same declension, I can reduce the cognitive overwhelm and increate the ease and speed with which my students acquire new vocabulary and grammar.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="teaching"></category></entry></feed>