<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://amindforlanguage.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://amindforlanguage.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-23T21:19:18-04:00</updated><id>https://amindforlanguage.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">A mind for language</title><subtitle>Posts by Fletcher Hardison on language learning, Python, and memory stuff. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Anki cloze cards for learning paradigms</title><link href="https://amindforlanguage.com/greek/2022/08/23/anki_tables.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anki cloze cards for learning paradigms" /><published>2022-08-23T11:23:32-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-23T11:23:32-04:00</updated><id>https://amindforlanguage.com/greek/2022/08/23/anki_tables</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amindforlanguage.com/greek/2022/08/23/anki_tables.html"><![CDATA[<p>Comprehensible input is the way to go. The research in second
language acquisition indicates that consciously memorized knowledge
can’t morph into facility with a language in the brain. The brain builds
its own black-box model of a language through our interaction with it.
This process relies on <em>understanding</em> the <em>meaning</em> of
what we read or hear, not on understanding the grammar.</p>
<p>In my experience, having familiarity with the paradigms and tables
<em>helps</em> figure out what an unfamiliar form in the text it. At
least it helps me think through whether this is a new form or a
completely new word. This in turns helps make unfamiliar things more
understandable. This increasing my ability to understand is the pay off,
not the conscious knowledge of the grammar.</p>
<p>Memorizing tables is a pain and is probably not worth too much
effort. Familiarity, however, has been helpful to me. The following is a
method to use Anki<span
class="sidenote-wrapper"><label for="sn-0" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-0" class="margin-toggle"/><span
class="sidenote">Free, SRS flashcard software, <a
href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/"
class="uri">https://apps.ankiweb.net/</a><br />
<br />
</span></span> and cloze deletion flashcards to help with this process
of building familiarity.</p>
<section id="what-is-a-cloze-card" class="level1">
<h1>What is a cloze card?</h1>
<p>A cloze card is a flashcard where the piece of information to be
learned it blanked out or deleted. This blanked out info is called a
“cloze deletion”. When studying our task is to recall the missing
piece.</p>
<p>Our brain remembers things better if we can form associations between
the new information and other things that we know. The more connections,
the stronger the memory and the easier the recall.</p>
<p>So instead of trying to memorize and recall a whole paradigm, I
propose that we use cloze deletions and blank out only a few pieces of
the paradigm.</p>
<p>The advantage is that we are only asking ourselves to recall a few
forms at a time. This lowers our stress and makes our minds more open to
receiving the information. Also we are seeing the other forms on the
table and thus seeing the connections between the current form and the
rest of the paradigm.</p>
<p>For example if we wanted to learn or become familiar with the
following paradigm:</p>
<h2 id="one">
<br>
</h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Masc
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Fem
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Neut
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">
NOM SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
εῖς
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μία
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
έν
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">
GEN SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενός
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μιᾶς
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενός
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">
DAT SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενί
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μιᾷ
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενί
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">
ACC SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ένα
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μίαν
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
έν
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>We could create cloze cards as follows in order to learn the Masc and
Neut, NOM SG forms:</p>
<h2 id="one">
<br>
</h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Masc
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Fem
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Neut
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">
NOM SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
[…]
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μία
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
[…]
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">
GEN SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενός
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μιᾶς
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενός
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">
DAT SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενί
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μιᾷ
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενί
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">
ACC SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ένα
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μίαν
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
έν
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Then the following could be used for the Masc and Neut Gen SG
forms:</p>
<h2 id="one">
<br>
</h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Masc
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Fem
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Neut
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">
NOM SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
εῖς
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μία
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
έν
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">
GEN SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
[…]
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μιᾶς
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
[…]
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">
DAT SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενί
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μιᾷ
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενί
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">
ACC SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ένα
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μίαν
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
έν
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>And the following to learn the Fem, Gen SG form:</p>
<h2 id="one">
<br>
</h2>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Masc
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Fem
</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">
Neut
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">
NOM SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
εῖς
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
[…]
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
έν
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">
GEN SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενός
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μιᾶς
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενός
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">
DAT SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενί
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μιᾷ
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ενί
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">
ACC SG
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
ένα
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
μίαν
</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">
έν
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>We could proceed by adding cloze deletions for the other pieces of
the paradigm that we want to recall. Note that it may not be necessary
to create a cloze deletion for every piece of the table. Remember that
the goal is familiarity.</p>
</section>
<section id="creating-tables-in-anki" class="level1">
<h1>Creating tables in Anki</h1>
<p>Anki includes a cloze deletion card type. The trick is the table. You
can either use spaces or tabs to format the table manually or you can
use HTML.</p>
<section id="spaces-and-tabs" class="level2">
<h2>Spaces and tabs</h2>
<p>Spaces and tables would be the simplest, but the result may not look
as nice. You have to manually line up the columns. I the result would be
as follows.</p>
<pre><code>       Masc Fem  Neut
NOM SG εῖς  μία     έν
GEN SG ενός μιᾶς ενός
DAT SG ενί  μιᾷ    ενί
ACC SG ένα  μίαν έν</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="html-tables" class="level2">
<h2>HTML tables</h2>
<p>The following instruction assume you are using the Desktop version of
Anki to create the cards. Once you sync your collection to your phone,
you can view the html tables there too.</p>
<p>Either you have to write the HTML manually, or you can use an HTML
table generator such as <a
href="https://www.tablesgenerator.com/html_tables">tablesgenerator.com</a>.</p>
<p>Once you have your html code, click <code>Add</code> to add a card.
Select the cloze card type. Then click on the field under the label
<code>Text</code>. After that, click on the three horizontal bars on the
right size of the formatting bar. After that select
<code>Edit HTML</code> or hit <code>CTRL + SHIFT + X</code> then paste
the html code into the pop-up and click <code>close</code>.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="creating-the-cloze-deletions" class="level1">
<h1>Creating the cloze deletions</h1>
<p>The following assume the desktop app, but the process is very similar
for creating cloze deletions on the mobile apps.</p>
<p>To create a cloze deletion, you first select the text you want to
turn into recall and click on the button <code>[...]</code> button on
the format bar or hit <code>CTRL + SHIFT + C</code>. This will wrap the
info in a cloze code that looks like ``.</p>
<p>You can create multiple cloze deletions per card. <code>c1</code>
will be the first, then <code>c2</code> will be the second, and so
forth.</p>
<p>If you want to have multiple pieces of the table blanked out at the
same time, edit the number following the <code>c</code> so they that
they are the same. For example, if I wanted ‘εν’ and ‘λογος’ to be cloze
deletions at the same time, I need to manually edit the number following
the <code>c</code> so that it looks like <code>αρχη ην</code>.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level1">
<h1>Final thoughts</h1>
<p>Should creating and studying flashcard in Anki replace other learning
activities that focus on comprehensible input? No. But they might be a
useful parallel activity.</p>
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="greek" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Comprehensible input is the way to go. The research in second language acquisition indicates that consciously memorized knowledge can’t morph into facility with a language in the brain. The brain builds its own black-box model of a language through our interaction with it. This process relies on understanding the meaning of what we read or hear, not on understanding the grammar.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring John’s vocabulary vs the rest of the GNT</title><link href="https://amindforlanguage.com/greek/2022/08/23/john-stats.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring John’s vocabulary vs the rest of the GNT" /><published>2022-08-23T11:23:32-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-23T11:23:32-04:00</updated><id>https://amindforlanguage.com/greek/2022/08/23/john-stats</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amindforlanguage.com/greek/2022/08/23/john-stats.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been considering the virtues of a NT Greek textbook oriented
around reading John’s Gospel. Clyde Pharr’s Homeric Greek textbook
(Pharr 1929) is built around reading Iliad, Book 1 and I think this has
some really helpful features.</p>
<p>The main advantage is that the exercises and readings all center
around a real text to be read and thus maintain a coherent storyline and
set of vocabulary. This approach is skewed in that it teaches for a
particular book, but in my mind the tradeoff is worth it.</p>
<p>That said I was wondering how the how many of the GNT lemmas one
would encounter reading John. In other words, how skewed would such an
approach be. So I clobbed together some code using James Tauber’s
<code>vocabulary tools</code><span
class="sidenote-wrapper"><label for="sn-0" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-0" class="margin-toggle"/><span
class="sidenote"><a href="https://github.com/jtauber/vocabulary-tools"
class="uri">https://github.com/jtauber/vocabulary-tools</a><br />
<br />
</span></span></p>
<section id="the-numbers" class="level1">
<h1>The numbers</h1>
<p>The table below shows some basic stats about the words and lemmas in
John and the GNT.<span
class="sidenote-wrapper"><label for="sn-1" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-1" class="margin-toggle"/><span
class="sidenote"><a
href="https://gist.github.com/fhardison/2e36ad765e1b4ab6dd5a06ae061cb44c">This
gist</a> has the code that generated the following statistics.<br />
<br />
</span></span></p>
<table>
<tr>
<td>
</td>
<td>
Words
</td>
<td>
Unique lemmas
</td>
<td>
Unique forms
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
John
</td>
<td>
15,438
</td>
<td>
999
</td>
<td>
2,571
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
GNT
</td>
<td>
137,554
</td>
<td>
5,461
</td>
<td>
17,566
</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>After learning John’s lemmas a learner would know 18.29% of the GNT’s
unique lemmas. Which is not so great.</p>
<p>The picture changes if we look at what percentage of the total words
in the GNT are occurrences of the lemmas in John.</p>
<p>The lemmas that occur in John cover 85.82% of the total of 137,554
lemmas that occur in the GNT. That’s not too shabby.</p>
<p>So after reading John, assuming a learner has a perfect memory, they
should be able to read 85.82% of the words they encounter in the rest of
the GNT.</p>
<p>But what about word forms? How many of the forms of words would a
reader encounter in John?</p>
<p>By reading John a reader would encounter 14.64% of the unique forms
found in the GNT. But these forms account for 74.63% of the 137,554
forms that occur in the GNT.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level1">
<h1>Conclusion</h1>
<p>By taking these two percentages of lemmas and forms vs total
occurrences in the GNT, it seems that John’s Gospel has a reasonable
amount of high frequency vocabulary and grammar. It seems that a learner
would be in a good place after reading John’s Gospel from whence to
explore the rest of the GNT, especially with the help of a reader’s
edition.</p>
<p>To me this shows that a NT Greek textbook oriented around reading
John’s Gospel would be plausible and valuable for students.</p>
</section>
<section id="bibliography" class="level1">
<h1>Bibliography</h1>
<div id="ref-pharr1920" class="csl-entry" role="doc-biblioentry">
Pharr, Clyde. 1920. <em>Homeric Greek: A Book for Beginners</em>.
Boston; New York; Chicago: D. C. Heath &amp; Co., Publishers.
</div>
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="greek" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been considering the virtues of a NT Greek textbook oriented around reading John’s Gospel. Clyde Pharr’s Homeric Greek textbook (Pharr 1929) is built around reading Iliad, Book 1 and I think this has some really helpful features.]]></summary></entry></feed>